Guide to the Papers of William Halsey Wood c.1865-1973 MS 000
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
William Halsey Wood Papers
1875-1973 (Bulk 1875-1897)
MS 000
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
4.0 Linear feet (3 archives boxes, 1 flat box)
The William Halsey Wood Papers consist of architectural drawings, photographs, personal correspondence, clippings, and other material related to the life of the architect William Halsey Wood (1885-1897).
Wood, William Halsey, 1855-1897
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, architectural drawings, photographs, clippings, and other material related to the personal and professional life of William Halsey Wood. A primary focus is his design for the Cathedral of St. John the Divine. Additionally, there are drawings and clippings related to some two dozen additional projects, the majority of which are churches. The design for his home in Newark, NJ is also prominent. Correspondence and other personal materials describe the architect's youth and wedding, followed later by his death at the age of 41.
Provenance
A gift of William Halsey Wood Jr. and Emily Hemsley Burrows (children), 1955.
Biographical/Historical note
William Halsey Wood (1855-1897) was born on April 24, 1855 in Danville, NY to Daniel Halsey Wood and Hannah Bell Lippincott. The family moved to Newark, NJ, where Halsey Wood was educated at the Episcopal House of Prayer parish school. In 1870 he began an apprenticeship with the architect John F. Miller in Newark. After leaving the unsuccessful firm Taylor, Roberts and Wood, he opened his own office in 1879. The same year, he completed the William Clark House, which was followed by a number of other notable domestic projects, including his own home, “Winmarleigh”.
His ecclesiastical designs, meanwhile, reached a height in 1888, when he entered his drawings for “Jerusalem, the Golden” into the design competition for the Cathedral of St. John the Divine in New York City. While his design was not ultimately accepted, he continued to work on a number of other prominent religious buildings, primarily Episcopal churches in New Jersey and New York. Like other noteworthy architects of the period, he tended to embrace a version of eclecticism that combined historic European styles with modern American sensibilities.
In 1889 he married Florence Hemsley in Tannersville, NY. They had three children. Halsey Wood died in 1897 in Philadelphia, PA at age 41.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two primary series: Personal Papers and Project Records. The former contains personal and biographical material and the latter documents the architectural output of William Halsey Wood. A third series contains mainly secondary source material sent to the repository decades after the initial donation.
Series I: Personal Papers
Series II: Project Records
Series III: Additional Accession
Material is arranged chronologically and by subject or format where appropriate. See series descriptions for more detail.
Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919; Architectural drawings (visual works); Architecture - United States; Architecture -- Competitions -- United States; Church buildings–New York (State)--New York--Design and construction; Clippings; Correspondence; Manhattan (N.Y.); Newark, N.J.; Photographic prints; Sketchbooks; Weddings--United States
- Series I: Personal Papers, c.1865-1938
  Scope and Contents
  The personal papers consist of correspondence, travel sketches, and biographical material related to the life and death of William Halsey Wood.
  - Subseries A: Correspondence, 1889-1897
    The correspondence consists primarily of letters written by William Halsey Wood to his fiancé Florence Hemsley in the months leading up their marriage in 1889. Wedding preparations are the focus of this correspondence, but there is also mention of the work being done on Peddie Memorial Church, the plans for the Cathedral of Saint John the Divine, and a meeting with Andrew Carnegie. There are also letters to WHW from Florence Hemsley (Florence H. Wood) and her mother, Emily Hemsley, as well as correspondence regarding the illness and death of WHW. The correspondence is partially catalogued at item level in the onsite manuscript card catalog.
    - William Halsey Wood to Florence Hemsley, September 8-15, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - William Halsey Wood to Florence Hemsley, September 16 - October 4, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - William Halsey Wood to Florence Hemsley, October 7-15, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - William Halsey Wood to Florence Hemsley, October 16-25, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - William Halsey Wood to Florence Hemsley, November 3-13, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Outgoing from William Halsey Wood, additional recipients, 1890-1897 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Florence Hemsley to William Halsey Wood, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Emily Hemsley to William Halsey Wood, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Various senders re: wedding, illness and death, 1889, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries B: Sketchbooks, 1875-1881
    There are two sketchbooks. The first (1875-1876) contains rough drawings of existing buildings and hypothetical designs. The latter contains drawings from a European trip in July and August 1881. Both are reflective of Halsey Wood’s design education.
    - Early sketchbook, 1875-1876 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Travel sketchbook, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Subseries C: Biographical Records, c.1865-1938
    The subseries contains a copy of "Memories of William Halsey Wood by his wife" (Florence Hemsley Wood), accompanied by additional copies of plates and illustrations. There are also memorial and obituary clippings, a will, and related ephemera.
    - Personal ephemera, 1889-1918 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Portraits, c.1865-c.1890 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Memories of William Halsey Wood" by his wife [Florence H. Wood], 1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Illustrations from "Memories of William Halsey Wood", 1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - St. Hilda's Guild photographs, c.1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Series II: Project Documents, 1885-1982 (Bulk 1885-1902)
  Project documents consist of original drawings and secondary material documenting the architectural work of William Halsey Wood.
  - Subseries A: Drawings, c.1885-c.1895
    Files contain original drawings reflecting William Halsey Wood's professional practice in various design phases. Included are sketches, details and perspectives on paper.
    - Cathedral of St. John the Divine - New York, NY, c. 1888 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Winmarleigh" Residence - Newark, NJ, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - St. John’s Episcopal Church - Cohoes, NY, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - St. Paul’s Episcopal Church - East Orange, NJ, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - St. John the Evangelist Episcopal Church - Tannersville, NY, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - St. Matthew’s Episcopal Church - New York, NY, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Newton Parish House - Newton, NJ, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Trask residence, unidentified, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified residential and religious buildings (Box 4, Folder 7, Folder 6)
  - Subseries B: Reference Files, 1889-1982 (Bulk 1889-1905)
    The subseries contains pamphlets, clippings, prints, and other secondary material related to the architectural work of William Halsey Wood.
    - Scrapbook, primarily St. John the Divine, 1889-1891 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Cathedral of St. John the Divine printed material, 1889-1982 (Box 3, Folder 4, Folder 3)
    - Churches, printed material, 1889-1906 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Winmarleigh, photographs and printed material, 1897-1902 (Box 3, Folder 6, Folder 7)
    - Oversize project images, primarily Winmarleigh, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series III: Additional Donation, 1968-1976
  This series consists of a group of later donations made by William Halsey Wood Jr., the son of the late architect. It contains correspondence, academic work, and other supplementary material.
  - William Halsey Wood Jr. correspondence and supplementary material, 1968-1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - R. Craig Miller correspondence and academic work, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)